Team WAF
We Are Family
Sub2smi by
WAF - 하늘님
미국 공군이
밝히는 바로는
그들은 이 영화에서
보여주는 사건들을
방지할 수 있다고 한다
영화에 등장하는
어떤 인물도
실존인물이 아님을
밝히는 바이다
1년이 넘게 서방 지도자들
사이에선
For more than a year, ominous rumors
had been privately circulating...
...among high-level Western leaders...
소련이 비밀리에
치명적 무기인
심판의 무기를
...that the Soviet Union had been at work
on what was darkly hinted to be...
준비 중이란 불길한
소문이 돌고 있었다
...the ultimate weapon:
a doomsday device.
정보국에선 끊임없는
추적으로 기밀연구소가
Intelligence sources traced the site
of the top-secret Russian project...
북극 아래 안개에 싸인
...to the perpetually
fog-shrouded wasteland...
조코프 섬에 있다는 걸
알아냈다
...below the Arctic peaks
of the Zhokhov Islands.
그렇게 외진 곳에서
무엇을 진행 중인지는
What they were building or why it was
located in a remote, desolate place...
아무도 알 수 없었다
...no one could say.
닥터 스트레인지러브
부제 : 걱정을 멈추고
폭탄을 사랑하게 된 이유
리퍼 장군이십니다
General Ripper, sir.
맨드레이크 대령입니다
Group Captain Mandrake speaking.
This is General Ripper speaking.
리퍼 장군이다
- 네
- 내 목소리 알아듣겠나?
- Yes, sir.
- Do you recognize my voice?
I do, sir. Why do you ask?
그렇습니다, 왜 물으시죠?
Why do you think?
왜 물었다고 생각하나?
I don't know, sir. We spoke
just a few moments ago, didn't we?
글쎄요, 몇 분 전에도
통화하지 않았습니까?
You don't think I'd ask unless it was
pretty damned important, do you?
중요하지 않은데도
내가 그런 걸 묻겠나?
No, I don't.
그렇겠죠
경계상태 확인 중이네
Let's see if we can stay on the ball.
Has the Wing confirmed holding
at their fail-safe points?
연대의 비상 안전장치는
확인됐나?
네, 방금 확인 받았습니다
Yes, sir. The confirmations
have just come in.
Very well.
Now, listen to me carefully.
좋아, 내 말 잘 듣게
The base is being put on condition red.
적색 경보가 내려졌네
전기지에도 즉시 알리게
I want this flashed
to all sections immediately.
Condition red. Jolly good.
Keeps the men on their toes.
적색 경보라, 대원들에게
긴장감도 주고 잘 됐군요
훈련 상황이 아니네
This is not an exercise.
Not an exercise?
훈련이 아니라고요?
I shouldn't tell you this, but you're
a good officer and have a right to know.
자넨 훌륭한 장교니
특별히 사실을 말해주지
이건 전시 상황이네
It looks like we're in a shooting war.
- 세상에, 소련의 침공입니까?
- 그것까진 모르겠네
- Oh, hell. Are the Russians involved?
- That's all I've been told.
긴급 상황이었지, 명령대로
기지를 봉쇄해야 한다네
It came in on the red phone. I'm gonna
follow orders and seal this base tight.
본부에는 R작전을 편다고
Now, I want you to transmit Plan R...
통보하게나
...R for Robert, to the Wing.
- Plan R for Robert.
- Is it that bad, sir?
- 철자 R이야
- 심각합니까?
- 등골이 오싹할 정도야
- 알겠습니다
- Looks like it's pretty hairy.
- Yes, sir.
Plan R for Robert.
즉시 통보하죠
Last and possibly most important...
그리고 가장 중요한 건
기지 내 모든 라디오를
즉각 수거하라는 거야
I want all privately owned radios
to be immediately impounded.
They might be used to issue
instructions to saboteurs.
놈들이 파괴공작에
이용할 수 있으니 말야
공군 헌병대에 라디오 소지자
명단이 있다네
As I previously arranged, Air Police
will have lists of all owners.
하나도 빠짐없이 수거하게나
I want every one collected
without exception.
임무수행 후
보고하게나
After you've done that,
report back to me.
In order to guard against
surprise nuclear attack...
적의 핵 공격에 대비하여
...America's Strategic Air Command
maintains...
미국 전략 공군 사령부
지휘 하에
B-52폭격대가
24시간 대기중이다
...a large force of B-52 bombers
airborne 24 hours a day.
Each B-52 can deliver
a nuclear bombload of 50 megatons...
B-52 전투기에 탑재된
50 메가톤의 핵 폭탄은
...equal to 16 times the total
explosive force of all the bombs...
2차 세계 대전 중 사용됐던
모든 폭발물의
...and shells used by all the armies
in World War II.
16배의 위력에 달한다
미국에 기지를 둔
공중 경비대는
Based in America,
the Airborne Alert Force...
폐르시아 만에서
북극해까지 배치돼있다.
...is deployed from the Persian Gulf
to the Arctic Ocean.
이들의 지리학적 공통점은
But they have one geographical factor
in common.
소련으로부터 2시간
사정권 안에 있다는 것이다
They are all two hours
from their targets inside Russia.
플레이보이
일급 비밀
항공 통신 암호
R침략 계획
Major Kong, I know you'll think
this is crazy...
소령님
정신 나간 소리 같지만
C.R.M. 114 기지의 연락인데
...but I just got a message from base
over the C.R.M. 114.
It decodes as Wing attack Plan R.
R for Romeo.
R침략 계획으로 해독됩니다
지금 R침략 계획이라 했나?
Goldie, did you say
Wing attack Plan R?
Yes, sir, I have.
그렇습니다
장난치지 말라고
몇 번을 말해야
Goldie, how many times have
I told you guys that I don't want...
...horsin' around on the airplane?
알아듣겠나?
I'm not horsing around.
That's how it decodes.
해독된 대로 말씀 드린 겁니다
I've been to one world fair,
a picnic...
여태 이곳 저곳
안 가본 데가 없지만
그런 황당한 얘긴 처음 듣네
...and rodeo, and that's the stupidest
thing I heard over earphones.
You sure you got today's code?
오늘의 암호가 맞나?
Yes, sir.
그렇습니다
착오가 있을 걸세
There's gotta be something wrong.
내가 곧 가겠네
Wait a second, I'm coming back.
기지로부터 재확인 받게나
Maybe you'd better get
a confirmation from base.
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다
충성심 테스트 같은 게
아닐까요?
Major Kong, is it possible
this is some kind of loyalty test?
누가 명령을 제대로
수행하는지 보려구요
You know, give the go code and then
recall to see who would actually go?
Ain't nobody ever got
the go code yet.
공격 명령은 처음이야
소련이 몰래 워싱턴과
다른 도시까지
Old Ripper wouldn't be giving us
Plan R...
침공하지 않았다면
리퍼 장군이
...unless them Ruskies had already
clobbered Washington...
그런 명령을 내릴 리 없지
...and a lot of other towns
with a sneak attack.
그렇습니다
Yes, sir.
Major Kong,
message from base confirmed.
명령 재확인 됐습니다
그렇다면 확실하군
Well, boys, I reckon this is it.
소련과의 핵 전쟁이다
Nuclear combat toe-to-toe
with the Ruskies.
Boys, I ain't much of a hand
at making speeches.
대원들, 연설할 상황은
아니지만
조국에 심상치 않은 일이
생긴 게
But I got a fair idea
that something doggone important...
틀림없다
...is going on back there.
대원들이 무슨 생각을 하는지
I've got a fair idea of the kind
of personal emotions...
...that some of you fellows
maybe thinking.
미루어 짐작이 간다
핵 전쟁에 대한
두려움 이 없다면
Heck, I reckon you wouldn't be
human beings...
그건 인간도 아니겠지
...if you didn't have pretty strong
personal feelings about nuclear combat.
I want you to remember one thing.
하지만 명심하라
조국의 가족들은
우리만 바라보고 있다
The folks back home
are counting on you.
And by golly,
we ain't about to let them down.
그들을 실망시켜선 안되지
그리고 한 가지 더...
Tell you something else.
사태가 내 짐작의
반만큼 이라도 심각하다면
If this thing turns out to be half
as important as I figure it might be...
...I'd say you're all in line
for some important promotions...
사태가 끝날 무렵에는
모두 진급하거나
표창을 받게 될 것이다
...and personal citations
when this thing's over with.
인종이나 피부색, 종교에
관계 없이
That goes for every last one of you...
공평하게 돌아간다
...regardless of your race,
color or your creed.
그러니 모두 전투 태세로
들어간다
Now let's get this thing on the hump.
We got some flying to do.
전화 받을까요?
Buck, should I get it?
Yeah, you'll have to.
그럼
여보세요?
Hello?
계시지만 전화는
받으실 수 없습니다
Yes, General Turgidson is here,
but he can't come to the phone now.
전 비서, 스캇입니다
This is his secretary, Miss Scott.
대령님?
안녕하셨어요?
Freddie, how are you?
Fine. And you?
그럼요
서류를 정리하고 있었습니다
Oh, we were just catching up
on some of the general's paperwork.
전화를 받으실 수 없는
상황이에요
He's tied up.
I'm afraid he can't come to the phone.
잠깐만요
Just a minute.
장군님
펀트리치 대령님 전화예요
General Turgidson,
a Colonel Puntrich calling.
다시 하라고 해
Tell him to call back.
잠시 후 다시 걸라는군요
Freddie, the general says
could you call back in a minute?
He says it can't wait.
급하다는데요
For Pete's--
Find out what he wants.
젠장, 무슨 일이래?
실은 화장실에 계신데
The general is in the powder room
right now.
무슨 일이죠?
Could you tell me what it's about?
8분전 버펠슨 공군 기지에서
Just a second. Apparently they monitored
a transmission eight minutes ago...
메시지가 왔는데
...from Burpelson Air Force Base.
843대 폭격대에
보낸 전문으로
Right. It was directed to
the 843rd Bomb Wing on airborne alert.
R침략 작전으로
해독됐답니다
It decoded as Wing attack Plan R.
그럼 기지 사령관
리퍼한테 전화하라고 해
Well, tell him to call what's-his-name,
Base Commander Ripper.
일일이 다 말해야 해?
Do I have to think of everything?
843 기지의 리퍼 사령관에게
연락하시랍니다
The general suggests you call General
Ripper, the 843rd base commander.
통신이 모두
두절 됐답니다
Oh. All communications are dead!
직접 연락해 보라고 해
Bull! Tell him to do it himself.
직접 연락을
취해 보라는데요
The general asks if you could
possibly try again yourself.
여러 번 해봤는데
실패했다고 합니다
I see. He says he's tried personally
several times, but everything is dead.
일반 전화도
두절이랍니다
Even the normal phone lines
are shut down.
프레드, 나네
상황이 어떤가?
Fred? Buck.
What's it look like?
그래?
Yeah?
R작전이 확실해?
Well, are you sure
it's Plan R?
전시 상황도는 어때?
Huh. What's cooking
on the threat board?
아무 낌새 없다고?
Nothing? Nothing at all?
심상치 않군
I don't like the look of this.
그럼 이렇게 하게나
Tell you what you better do,
old buddy.
각 기지에 적색 경보를
내리는 거야
You better give Elmo and Charlie a blast
and bump everything up to condition red.
연락할 테니 기다리게
Stand by the blower.
I'll get back to you.
- 무슨 일이죠?
- 별거 아냐
- What's up?
- Nothing.
- 바지 어딨지?
- 바닥에요, 어디 가세요?
- Where's my shorts?
- On the floor. Where are you going?
별일 아냐
No place.
전시 상황실이 어떤지
잠깐 들러야겠어
I thought I might mosey over to the
War Room to see what's doing over there.
새벽 3시에요?
It's 3:00 in the morning.
The air force never sleeps.
공군은 항상 깨어있지
Buck, honey, I'm not sleepy either.
자기, 나도 잠이 안 와요
그 괴로움 알지
I know how it is, baby.
좋은수가 있어
Tell you what you do.
당신이 카운트다운 하면
발사 전에
You start your countdown
and old Buck will be back...
돌아오도록 할게
...before you can say "Blastoff!"
빨갱이들은 사람 목숨을
파리 목숨 취급하지
Your Commie has no regard
for human life, not even his own.
그러므로 대원들은
철통 같은 경계를
For this reason, men, I want
to impress upon you the need...
해야 한다
...for extreme watchfullness.
소규모 공격이든
대규모든
The enemy may come individually
or he may come in strength.
아군으로 가장하여
공격하든
He may even come in the uniform
of our own troops.
그들의 침입을
저지해야 하고
But however he comes,
We must stop him.
기지 안으로 들어오지
못하도록 하라
We must not allow him
to gain entrance to this base.
간단한 규칙 3가지를
하달하겠다
Now, I am going to give you
three simple rules.
첫째, 군복, 지위를 막론하고
아무도 믿지 말 것
First: Trust no one,
Whatever his uniform or rank...
낮선 자는
그 누구도 말이다
...unless he is known to you personally.
둘째, 그 누구든
Secondly: Anyone or anything...
경계선 2백 야드 내
접근자는 사격한다
...that approaches within 200 yards
of the perimeter is to be fired upon.
셋째, 조금이라도 이상하면
일단 사격한다
Third: If in doubt, shoot first
and ask questions afterwards.
기지 전체가 점령되는 걸
막기 위한
I would sooner accept a few casualties
through accident...
몇 명의 사상자는
묵과하겠다
...than lose the entire base
and its personnel through carelessness.
모든 명령은
내가 직접 내린다
Any variation on these rules
must come from me personally.
마지막으로
Now, men, in conclusion...
I would like to say
that in the two years...
하고 싶은 말은
지난 2년간
제군들의 사령관이었던 걸
영광으로 생각한다
...that it has been my privilege
to be your commanding officer...
...I have always expected
the best from you...
제군들에게
많은 기대를 했고
...and you have never given me
anything less than that.
실망한 적은 없었다
우리를
믿고 의지하는 조국을
Today the nation is counting on us.
실망시킬 순 없다
We are not going to let them down.
행운을 빈다
Good luck to you all.
일급비밀 R
Here's the attack profile, sir.
공격 명령서입니다
일급비밀 비행사
This is your attack profile.
공격 명령이다
적군의
음성 통신 모니터나
"To ensure that the enemy cannot monitor
voice transmission...
위장 송신을 막기 위해
...or plant false transmission...
C.R.M. 114는수신 회로로
변환한다
...the C.R.M. 114 is to be switched
into all receiver circuits.
The emergency base code prefix
is to be set...
비상 기지 암호 서두를
C.R.M. 표시판에 입력하라
...on the dials of the C.R.M.
이는 다른 통신의 방해를
막을 것이다
This will block any transmission other
than those preceded by a code prefix."
암호 입력 대기하라
Stand by to set code prefix.
Roger. Ready to set code prefix.
대기 중입니다
"Set code prefix."
암호 입력 모드
됐습니다
Code prefix set.
"Lock code prefix."
암호 고정
Code prefix locked.
암호 저장됐습니다
"Switch all receiver circuits
to C.R.M. discriminators."
수신 회로를 모두
C.R.M. 판별장치로 전환
Switched to C.R.M. discriminators.
C.R.M. 114 판별장치
C.R.M. 판별장치로 변환
자동 폭파회로 확인
"Check auto destruct circuits."
자동 폭파
확인됐습니다
Auto destruct circuits checked.
주요 공격 목표:
라퓨터의 I.C.B.M. 기지
"Primary target:
the I.C.B.M. complex at Laputa."
목표물 참조번호는
Y.G.T...
Target reference:
Yankee, golf, tango...
...3-6-0.
3-6-0
Thirty megaton nuclear device...
30메가톤급 핵 폭탄
1만 피트 상공에서 공격
...fused for airburst at 10,000 feet.
작동 불량 시
20메가톤급으로 대체
Twenty megaton nuclear device
will be used if first malfunctions.
다음 공격 목표는
Otherwise, proceed to secondary target:
missile complex seven miles east
of Borchov.
보르초프 동쪽 7마일의
미사일 기지로
목표물 참조 번호는
N.B.X...
Target reference:
November, bravo, Xray...
1-0-8
1-0-8.
1만 2천 피트
상공에서 공격
Fused air burst at 10--
Check-- 12,000 feet."
장군님
뭔가 이상합니다
Excuse me, sir. Something rather
interesting has just cropped up.
민간 방송에서
음악이 나옵니다
Listen to that. Music.
Civilian broadcasting.
국방성의 훈련 명령이
분명합니다
I think the Pentagon has given us
an exercise to check our readiness.
그럼 정말
심각합니다
I think it's taking things too far.
20분 후면 아군이
소련 사정권에 들어갑니다
Our fellows will be inside Russian
radar cover in about 20 minutes.
크게 틀을 테니
잘 들어보십시오
Listen. Chock full of stations
all churning it out.
- 맨드레이크?
- 네, 장군님?
- Mandrake?
- Yes, sir?
라디오는 모두
수거하라고 했을 텐데
I issued instructions for all radios
to be impounded.
수거하다가 우연히
틀게 된 겁니다
You did, and I was in the process of
impounding this when I switched it on.
정말 아군 폭격기가
소련을 공격한다면
I thought our fellows hitting Russian
radar, dropping all their stuff...
골치 아픈 일이
아닙니까?
...I'd better tell you because if they do,
it'll cause a stink.
장교 교환 프로그램이
Group Captain,
the officer exchange program...
뭐 그리 대단한 거라고
명령에 이의를 제기하나?
...does not give you any special
prerogatives to question my orders.
그저 소식을 전하고
싶었을 뿐입니다
I realize that, sir, but I thought
you'd be pleased to hear the news.
솔직히 누가...
After all, let's face it.
We don't want to start a nuclear war
unless we have to, do we?
핵전쟁을 시작하고
싶겠습니까?
앉게나
라디오는 끄고
Please sit down.
And turn that thing off.
알겠습니다
Yes, sir.
폭격기 철수 명령부터
해야 되지 않을까요?
What about the planes? Surely we must
issue the recall code immediately.
철수는 없을 거네
The planes are not going
to be recalled.
내 공격 명령은
변함 없지
My attack orders have been issued,
and the orders stand.
무례한 말씀이지만
제 생각에 그건...
If you'll excuse me for saying so,
that would be to my way of thinking...
현명한 판단이
아닌 듯 합니다
...rather an odd way of looking at it
소련이
정말 침공했다면
If a Russian attack was in progress...
민간 방송이
나올 리 없죠
...we would certainly not be hearing
civilian broadcasting.
- 정말인가?
- 물론이죠
- Are you certain?
- I'm absolutely positive.
만약 그렇다면?
What if it is true?
그럼 더욱 명령에
복종할 수 없습니다
I'm afraid I'm still not with you, sir,
because I mean...
소련이 침공한 게
아니라면
...if a Russian attack
was not in progress...
전 공군에 R작전 명령을
내리는 건...
...then your use of Plan R-- In fact,
your orders to the entire Wing--...
뭔가 굉장히
잘못된 겁니다
...I would say, sir, that there was
something dreadfully wrong somewhere.
대령, 진정하게나
Why don't you take it easy,
Group Captain?
나한테
술 한잔 갖다 주고
Please make me a drink
of grain alcohol and rainwater...
자네도
한잔 하지 그러나?
...and help yourself
to whatever you'd like.
리퍼 장군님
영국 공군 장교로서
General Ripper, sir, as an officer
in Her Majesty's Air Force...
현 상황을 고려할 때
제가 할 일은
...it is my clear duty
under the present circumstances...
명령 취하 암호를 보내
폭격기를 귀환시키는 겁니다
...to issue the recall code upon my
own authority and bring back the Wing.
이만 물러가겠습니다
If you'll excuse me, sir.
Sir, I must ask you for the key and the
recall code. Have you got them handy?
열쇠와 취하 암호를 주십시오
물론 있겠죠?
진정하라고
했을 텐데
I told you to take it easy,
Group Captain.
이젠 그누구도
어쩔 수 없네
There's nothing anybody can do now.
암호를 아는 건
나뿐이니까
I'm the only person who knows
the three-letter code group.
I must insist
that you give them to me!
제게도
알려주십시오!
절 총으로
위협하는 겁니까?
Do I take it, sir, you are threatening
a brother officer with a gun?
맨드레이크
자넨 모르겠지만
Mandrake, I suppose
it never occurred to you...
우리가 한가하게 사담을
나누는 동안
...that while we're chatting here
so enjoyably...
국방성 전시 상황실의
대통령과
...a decision is being made
by the president...
...and the joint chiefs in the War Room
at the Pentagon.
합동 참모들은
회의를 하고 있네
그들이 공격 명령 취소가
불가능하다는 걸 안다면
When they realize there is
no possibility of recalling the Wing...
앞으로 일어날 일은
뻔하네
...there will be only one course
of action open.
사태를
지켜볼수밖에
Total commitment.
정치가 클레망소가
했던 말 기억하나?
Mandrake, do you recall what
Clemenceau once said about war?
잘 모르겠습니다
No, I don't think I do, sir. No.
전쟁은 군인 손에
맡기기엔 너무 중요하다
He said war was too important
to be left to the generals.
그 말을 했던
50년 전엔
When he said that 50 years ago...
설득력이 있었겠지
...he might have been right.
하지만 오늘날...
But today...
정치인에게는 더욱
맡길수 없지
...war is too important
to be left to politicians.
정치가에겐
시간도 훈련도
They have neither the time,
the training...
전략적
머리 따위도 없어
...nor the inclination
for strategic thought.
더 이상
두고 볼수가 없었지
I can no longer sit back
and allow...
공산주의의 침투와
공산주의의 유입...
...Communist infiltration,
Communist indoctrination...
공산주의의 파괴...
...Communist subversion...
그리고 소중한
우리의 체액을
...and the international
Communist conspiracy...
오염시키는
...to sap and impurify...
국제적인 공산주의
음모를 말야
...all of our precious
bodily fluids.
모두 모였나?
Staines, is everybody here?
국무장관님은 베트남에
Mr. President, the secretary of state
is in Vietnam.
국방장관님은 라오스에
부통령은 멕시코에 계십니다
The secretary of defense is in Laos, and
the vice president is in Mexico City.
We can establish contact with them at
anytime. The undersecretaries are here.
언제든 연락이 가능하고
차관들은 참석했습니다
터지슨 장군
대체 무슨 일인가?
Right. General Turgidson,
what's going on?
대통령 각하
Mr. President...
약 35분 전
...about 35 minutes ago...
버펠슨 공군기지 사령관인
...General Jack Ripper,
the commanding general...
잭 리퍼 장군이
...of Burpelson Air Force Base...
당시 초계 근무 중인
자신 휘하의
...issued an order to the 34 B-52s
of his Wing...
34 B-52 폭격대에
...which were airborne at the time...
작전 드롭킥이라는
훈련 명령을 내렸습니다
...as part of a special exercise we were
holding called Operation Dropkick.
그런데 명령 내용이
It appears that the order
called for the planes...
소련 내 목표물 공격입니다
...to attack their targets
inside Russia.
각 폭격기엔 40메가톤의
The planes are fully armed
with nuclear weapons...
...with an average load
of 40 megatons each.
핵무기를 탑재한 상태입니다
중앙 화면에 폭격기 위치가
표시됩니다
The central display of Russia will
indicate the position of the planes.
삼각형이 제1목표물이고
The triangles
are their primary targets.
사각형이 제2 목표물입니다
The squares
are their secondary targets.
폭격기는 25분 안에
소련 상공을 지나갈 겁니다
The aircraft will begin penetrating
Russian radar cover within 25 minutes.
장군, 이해하기 힘들군
General Turgidson, I find this
very difficult to understand.
핵무기 사용 명령 권한은
나에게만 있지 않소?
I understood I was the only one
to order the use of nuclear weapons.
그렇습니다
각하에게만 권한이 있죠
That's right, sir. You are
the only person authorized to do so.
성급하게
말씀 드리긴 싫지만
And although I hate to judge
before all the facts are in...
리퍼 장군이 권력을
남용한 것 같습니다
...it's beginning to look like
General Ripper exceeded his authority.
그렇군
상상도 못할 일이야
It certainly does, far beyond the point
I would have imagined possible.
R 작전의 규정을
잊고 계신 것 같군요
Perhaps you're forgetting
the provisions of Plan R, sir.
Plan R?
R 작전?
비상 전시 작전으로
Plan R is an emergency war plan...
적의 급습 시에는
낮은 지위의 사령관도
...in which a lower echelon commander
may order...
핵 보복 명령을
할 수 있습니다
...nuclear retaliation
after a sneak attack...
기존의 명령 체계가
붕괴되는 경우죠
...if the normal chain of command
has been disrupted.
각하께서 승인했던
작전입니다
You approved it, sir.
You must remember.
뷰포트 의원이 우리의
핵무기 사용 억제력이
Surely you must recall, sir,
when Senator Beaufort made...
허술하다고
소란을 피웠었죠
...that big hassle about our deterrent
lacking credibility.
R작전은 보복적인
방위수단입니다
The idea was for Plan R to be
a sort of retaliatory safeguard.
방위 수단?
A safeguard?
이번 일로 인간의 약점이
드러나게 됐지만 말입니다
I admit the human element seems
to have failed us here.
하지만 작전의 목적은
소련이 품고 있는
But the idea was to discourage
the Ruskies from any hope...
미합중국을 쑥대밭으로
만들수 있다는 헛된 생각을
...they could knock out Washington, and
yourself, as part of a sneak attack...
뿌리뽑고 신속한 대처능력을
보이기 위한 겁니다
...and escape retaliation because of lack
of proper command and control.
그래도 폭격대가
방위 한계선에 이르면
I assume the planes will return
automatically...
자동 회환 하겠지?
...once they reach their fail-safe points.
아닐 겁니다
방위 한계선 초계 중에
I'm afraid not. The planes were holding
at their fail-safe points...
...when the go code was issued.
공격 명령을
받았기 때문입니다
일단 한계선을 넘으면
더 이상의 명령은 불필요하죠
Once they fly beyond fail-safe, they do
not require a second order to proceed.
목표 지점까지 갈 겁니다
They will continue
until they reach their target.
그렇다면 왜 취소 명령을
하지 않았소?
Then why haven't you radioed the planes,
countermanding the go code?
연락 방법이
없기 때문입니다
We're unable to communicate
with any of the aircraft.
이유는?
Why?
기억하시겠지만
As you may recall, sir...
R 작전의 규정 중 하나가
...one of the provisions
of Plan R provides...
일단 공격 명령이 내려지면
...that once the go code
is received...
보통 S.S.B. 주파수는
...the normal S.S.B. radios
in the aircraft...
특수 암호 체계로
변환되는데
...are switched into
a special coded device...
C.R.M. 114로 불릴 겁니다
...which I believe is designated
as C.R.M. 114.
적의 교란 작전을
막기 위한 것으로
In order to prevent the enemy
from issuing fake or confusing orders...
...C.R.M. 114 is designed
not to receive at all...
C.R.M. 114는 세 문자의
비밀 암호가 없으면
전문 자체를 못 받도록
디자인돼있습니다
...unless the message is proceeded by the
correct three-letter code group prefix.
You mean to tell me you will be unable
to recall the aircraft?
폭격기를 불러들일
방법이 없단 말이오?
그렇습니다만
암호로 가능한
That's the size of it.
However, we are plowing through...
세 자리 글자를
조합해 보고 있는 중입니다
...every possible three-letter combination
of the code.
1만 7천 가지
조합이 가능하므로
But since there are
17,000 permutations...
약 이틀 반 정도가
소요됩니다
...it's going to take us about two
and a half days to transmit them all.
소련 레이더 망엔
언제 포착되겠소?
How soon will the planes penetrate
Russian radar cover?
- 약 18분 후입니다
- 리퍼 사령관과는 연락됐소?
-About 18 minutes from now.
-Are you in contact with General Ripper?
아뇨, 기지가 봉쇄되고
연락이 두절된 상태입니다
No, sir. General Ripper sealed off
the base and cut off communications.
정보는 어디서 얻었소?
Where did you get this information?
공격 명령 직후
전략 공군 사령부에
General Ripper called
Strategic Air Command Headquarters...
리퍼 장군이
연락을 했습니다
...shortly after he issued the go code.
괜찮으시다면 대화 내용
사본을 읽겠습니다
I have a portion of the conversation
transcript if you'd like me to read it.
읽으시오
Read it.
공격 명령 확인을 요청한
The duty officer asked
General Ripper...
근무장교에게
리퍼 장군이 말했습니다
...to confirm the fact that he had
issued the go code and he said:
그렇소, 그들을 저지할
방법은 없소
"Yes, gentlemen, they are on their way
in and no one can bring them back.
For the sake of our country
and our way of life...
국가와 국민을 위해
모두 전투에 참여하는 게
좋을 것이오
...I suggest you get the rest of SAC
in after them.
Otherwise, we will be totally destroyed
by Red retaliation.
그렇지 않으면 빨갱이들의
보복으로 초토화 되겠지
부하들이 1천 4백 메가톤의
핵무기로 멋지게 시작하면
My boys will give you the best kind
of start: 1,400 megatons worth.
그들을 막을 길은 없소
And you sure as hell
won't stop them now.
진격 이외에
다른 방법은 없소
So let's get going.
There's no other choice.
신의 뜻대로
우린 평화롭고 용감하게
God willing, we will prevail
in peace and freedom from fear...
...and in true health
through the purity...
타고난 체액의
순수함을 바탕으로...
패기 있게...
...and essence of our natural...
이길 것이오
...fluids.
신의 가호가 있기를
God bless you all."
그리곤 끊었습니다
Then he hung up.
마지막 말의 뜻은
아직 분석 중입니다
We're still trying to figure out
the meaning of that last phrase, sir.
분석할 것 없소
정신병자야
There's nothing to figure out.
This man is obviously a psychotic.
I'd like to hold off judgment
until all the facts are in.
전말을 알기 전엔
결론은 성급합니다
장군은
인성 신뢰도 측정으로
General Turgidson, when you instituted
the human reliability tests...
이런 일의 발생은 막을수
있다고 확신했잖소
...you assured me there was no possibility
of such a thing ever occurring.
한 번의 오류로
프로그램 자체를 비난하는 건
Well, I don't think it's fair
to condemn a whole program...
지나치십니다
...because of a single slip-up, sir.
리퍼 장군과
통화하고 싶소
I want to speak to General Ripper
on the telephone.
불가능합니다
That's impossible.
General Turgidson, I am becoming
less and less interested...
무엇이 가능하고
무엇이 불가능한지에 대한
장군의 가치판단에는
관심이 없소
...in your estimates
of what is possible and impossible.
폐이스먼 장군
General Faceman.
네, 각하?
Yes, sir?
버펠슨 근처에
다른 기지는 없소?
Are there any army units
stationed near Burpelson?
확인해보겠습니다
I'll just check, sir.
여보세요?
Hello?
전화하지 말라고 했잖아
여기가 어딘지 알고
I told you never to call me here.
Don't you know where I am?
지금은 곤란해
Look, baby, I can't talk to you now.
각하께서 부르셨지
My president needs me.
물론 나도
당신과 있고 싶어
Of course Bucky would rather
be there with you.
육체적인 이유만은 아냐
Of course it isn't only physical.
인간적으로
당신을 존경한다고
I deeply respect you
as a human being.
언젠간
내 아내로 맞겠어
Someday I'm going to make you
Mrs. Buck Turgidson.
이제 그만 자라고
Oh, listen, you go back to sleep.
가능한
빨리 돌아갈게
Buck will be there as soon as he can.
기도하고
자는 거 잊지 마
All right. Listen, don't forget
to say your prayers.
23 공군 기지가
Apparently,
the 23rd Airborne Division...
알바라도에서 7마일 떨어진
곳에 있습니다
...is stationed seven miles away
at Alvarado.
그들에게 기지로 들어가
리퍼 장군을 찾아
General Faceman, I want them to enter
the base, locate General Ripper...
나와 통화할 수 있도록
조치하라고 하시오
...and put him in immediate
telephone contact with me.
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다
대통령 각하?
Mr. President?
한 말씀 드리겠습니다
If I may advise.
적색 경보 하에서는
기지는 봉쇄되고
Under a condition red, it is standard
procedure that the base be sealed off...
철저히 방어되는 게
일반적입니다
...and the base defended
by base security troops.
잘못 들어가려 했다가
사상자만 늘어날 겁니다
Any force trying to enter would
certainly encounter heavy casualties.
General Turgidson, with all due respect
for your defense team...
터지슨 장군
충고는 고맙소만
내 부하들이 힘 안들이고
쓸어버릴 거요
...my boys can brush them aside
without too much trouble.
각하, 괜찮다면 몇 마디만
더 하겠습니다
Mr. President, there are one or two
points I'd like to make, if I may?
하시오
Go ahead, General.
첫째, 843 폭격대를
귀환 시킨다는 건
One: Our hopes for recalling
the 843rd Bomb Wing...
거의 불가능하다고
여겨집니다
...are quickly being reduced
to a very low order of probability.
둘째, 15분 후 소련도
Two: In less than 15 minutes
from now...
그들을
포착하게 될 겁니다
...the Ruskies will be making
radar contact with the planes.
셋째, 그렇게 되면
Three: When they do...
그들은 야만적으로
전면공격을 해오겠죠
...they will go absolutely ape and
strike back with everything they've got.
Four: If prior to this time...
넷째, 그 전에
그들의 보복성 대응을
저지 못한다면
...we have done nothing to suppress
their retaliatory capabilities...
파멸을
면치 못할 겁니다
...we will suffer virtual annihilation.
다섯째, 만약 반대로...
Five: lf, on the other hand...
적군의 비행장과
미사일 기지를 공격한다면
...we immediately launched an attack
on their airfields and missile bases...
그들의 허를 찌를수
있을 겁니다
...we'd stand a damn good chance
of catching them with their pants down.
미사일도 저들보다
5배나 많습니다
Hell, we've got
a five-to-one missile superiority.
목표물 당 미사일을
3개까지 쓸수 있고
We could easily assign three missiles
to every target...
어떤 상황에서도 대처할
능력이 있습니다
...and still have a very effective reserve
force for any other contingency.
여섯째, 비공식적인
연구에 따르면
Six: An unofficial study which
we undertook of this eventuality...
놈들의 핵 보유량을
90% 파괴시킬수 있다고 합니다
...indicated that we would destroy
90% of their nuclear capabilities.
약간의 민간인 희생만
감수한다면
We would therefore prevail...
우린 승리할 겁니다
...and suffer only modest and acceptable
civilian casualties...
적군은 심한 타격으로
와해될지도 모르죠
...from their remaining force which would
be badly damaged and uncoordinated.
핵 선제 공격은
General, it is the avowed policy
of our country...
국가 정책에 위배됩니다
...never to strike first
with nuclear weapons.
그 정책은 리퍼 장군이
이미 어겼습니다
Well, Mr. President, General Ripper
has already invalidated that policy.
국가정책에 반하는 행위였지만
아직 해결책은 있소
That was not an act of national policy.
There are still alternatives open to us.
각하, 진실에 가까워지고 있는
순간입니다
Mr. President, we are rapidly
approaching a moment of truth...
인류에게나 국가에게나
중요한 일이죠
...both for ourselves as human beings
and for the life of our nation.
진실이
유쾌할 수만은 없죠
Truth is not always a pleasant thing.
선택을 해야 할 때입니다
But it is necessary now
to make a choice:
양쪽의 어떤 선택도
내키지 않는 데다가
to choose between two admittedly
regrettable...
확연한
전시 상황일 겁니다
...but nevertheless distinguishable
postwar environments.
2천만 명의 희생과
150명의 희생이 있습니다
One, where 20 million people are killed;
the other, 150 people killed.
전쟁이 아니라
학살이잖소
You're talking about mass murder,
General, not war.
Mr. President, I'm not saying
we wouldn't get our hair mussed.
우리 쪽도 피해를
보는 게 당연합니다
하지만 많아야 1천만에서
2천만 정도 죽습니다
But I do say no more than
10 to 20 million killed. Tops!
상황에 따라 다르겠죠
Depending on the breaks.
히틀러 이후 최악의 살인마로
역사에 기록되긴 싫소
I will not go down in history as
the greatest mass murderer since Hitler!
역사책에 남을
이미지보다는
It might be better
if you were more concerned...
미국 국민을 먼저
걱정하셔야죠
...with the American people than
with your image in the history books.
장군의 말은
더 이상 듣기 싫소
General Turgidson,
I've heard quite sufficient from you.
고맙소
Thank you very much.
Mr. President, they have
the ambassador waiting upstairs.
위층에서 대사가
기다리고 계십니다
- 별일 없었나?
- 헌병 때문에 언짢은 상태죠
- Good. Any difficulty?
- He's having a fit about the M.P.s.
조짐이 안 좋군
당장 모셔오게
That can't be helped.
Have him brought here straightaway.
알겠습니다
Yes, sir.
소련 대사라고요?
Is that the Russian ambassador?
그렇소
Yes, it is, General.
그러니까 소련 대사를
Am I to understand
the Russian ambassador...
전시 상황실에
들여놓는다고요?
...is to be admitted entrance
to the War Room?
That is correct.
He is here on my orders.
그렇지, 내가 불렀소
어떻게 이런 일이...
I don't know exactly how
to put this, sir...
안보상 위험이 크다는 거
모르십니까?
...but are you aware of what a breach
of security that would be?
전시 배치도까지
다 보게 됩니다
He'll see everything.
He'll see the big board.
바로 그래서 모셨소
That is precisely the idea, General.
그래서 모시게 된 거지
That is precisely the idea.
키스오프 서기장에게
전화 하게
Staines, get Premier Kissoff
on the hot line.
생존 장비를 점검한다
"Survival kit contents check.
45구경 자동 소총 한 자루
In them you will find
one .45 caliber automatic...
탄약 두 상자
...two boxes of ammunition...
4일분 비상 식량과
...four days concentrated
emergency rations...
항생제를 비롯해
...one drug issue
containing antibiotics...
모르핀, 비타민제, 각성제...
...morphine, vitamin pills,
pep pills...
수면제, 진정제...
...sleeping pills,
tranquilizer pills...
...one miniature combination
Russian phrasebook and Bible...
소련어 관용어구 책과
성경책...
...$100 in rubles...
루블화 1백 달러
1백 달러어치 금
...$100 in gold...
껌 9통
...nine packs of chewing gum...
콘돔 1통
...one issue of prophylactics...
립스틱 3개
나일론 스타킹 3장
...three lipsticks,
three pair of nylon stockings."
이 정도면 라스베가스에서
멋진 주말을 보낼 수 있겠군
Shoot, a fellow could have a pretty
good weekend in Vegas with that stuff.
- 신선한 생선이 없다고?
- 그렇습니다
- You don't have any fresh fish?
- I'm afraid not, sir.
- 달걀은 신선하오?
- 그렇습니다
- Your eggs are fresh?
- Yes, sir.
수란이나 먹어야겠군
하바나산 시가 좀 부탁하네
I will have poached eggs. And bring me
some cigars, please. Havana cigars.
그거면 됩니까?
곧 가져오죠
That will be all, sir?
I'll see to it right away.
Try one of these Jamaican cigars,
Ambassador. They're good.
자메이카산 시가도
괜찮으니 피워 보시죠
사양하겠소
제국주의 물건은 내키지 않아
Thank you, no. I do not support the work
of imperialist stooges.
공산당원 것만 사시겠다?
Oh, only Commie stooges, huh?
Mr. President.
대통령 각하
악질 빨갱이 놈의
횡포를 가만 놔두실 건가요?
You're gonna let that lousy Commie punk
vomit all over us like this?
각하?
Mr. President?
서기장과 연락이 안되고
두 시간이나 지나야
They haven't reached Premier Kissoff.
They don't know where he is...
돌아온다고 합니다
...and he won't be back for two hours.
모스크바 B-8-6-5-4-3으로
보시오
Try B-8-6-5-4-3 Moscow.
서기장실로 해 봤자
소용 없을 거요
You would never have found him
through his office.
인민의 지도자인 동시에
남자이기도 하니까
Our premier is a man of the people,
but he is also a man, if you follow.
- 타락한 무신론적 공산주의자
- 뭐라 하셨소?
- Degenerate atheistic Commie.
- What did you say?
서기장은 타락한
무신론적 공산주의자라고!
I said Premier Kissoff is
a degenerate atheistic Commie!
- 이 멍청한 놈이...
- 죄송합니다
- Have this ignorant fool--
- I'm sorry!
각하, 계속 연락 중입니다
Mr. President,
I think they're trying the number.
전쟁 상황실에서
무슨 추태요?
Gentlemen, you can't fight in here.
This is the War Room!
왜들 그러시죠?
해명을 해주시오
What is going on here?
I demand an explanation.
이 멍청이가 내게 카메라를
설치하려 했소
This clumsy fool tried to plant
that ridiculous camera on me.
헛소리 마시오
이걸 보십쇼
You bet your sweets, Mr. Commie!
Look at this, Mr. President.
이 작자가 전시 배치도
사진을 찍고 있었습니다
This lousy Commie rat was taking
pictures with this of the big board!
대사
Mr. Ambassador!
이 바보가 내게 카메라를
설치하려 했소이다
This clumsy fool attempted to plant
that ridiculous camera on me.
거짓말입니다
제 눈으로 직접 봤습니다
That's a damn lie!
I saw him with my own eyes.
전시 상황실에서
이런 추태는 처음 보오
This is outrageous. I have never heard
of such behavior in the War Room before.
각하, 연결된 것 같습니다
Mr. President, I think
they're getting him on the line.
빨갱이들에게
한방 먹이는 거다
You got to hand it to those Commies.
진짜 아군 트럭 같이
생겼네요
Yeah. Those trucks sure look like
the real thing, don't they?
어디서
저런 걸 구했을까?
I wonder where they got them from.
무기 밀거래로 샀겠죠
Probably bought them
from the army as war surplus.
사정 거리 2백 야드
Okay, open up at 200 yards.
어딘지 밝히고
내가 거짓말을 하면
Tell him where you are and that
you'll speak if I say anything untrue...
알려준다고 하시오
...but nothing more than that.
대사?
제발 부탁이오
Alexi? Alexi, please.
I beg you.
But I don't have a phone.
하지만 전화가 없잖소
Give him the phone.
전화를 주게
부탁한 대로 했소만
술에 취했으니 조심하시오
I've done as you asked.
Be careful. I think he is drunk.
안녕하십니까, 서기장?
Hello? Hello, Dimitri?
나도 잘 안 들리오
Listen, I can't hear too well.
음악을 좀 낮추시죠
Could you turn the music down
a little?
훨씬 낫군요
That's much better.
그럼요
Yeah. Yeah.
이젠 잘 들립니다
Fine. I can hear you now, Dimitri.
깨끗하고 똑똑하게
잘 들린다고요
Clear and plain
and coming through fine.
제 말도 똑똑히 들립니까?
잘 됐군요
I'm coming through fine, too, eh?
Good.
그래요, 양쪽 다 똑똑히
들리니 좋군요
Well, then, as you say,
we're both coming through fine. Good.
It's good that you're fine...
잘 지낸다니
다행입니다
저도 잘 지냅니다
...and I'm fine.
맞아요
잘 지내는 건 좋은 거죠
I agree with you.
It's great to be fine.
이봐요...
Now, Dimitri...
우린 폭탄이 잘못 될
가능성에 대해
...you know how we've always talked
about the possibility...
많은 얘길 해왔었죠
...of something going wrong
with the bomb.
폭탄 말입니다
The bomb, Dimitri.
수소 폭탄요
The hydrogen bomb.
Well, now, what happened is...
그런데 말입니다
우리측 기지 사령관 하나가
...one of our base commanders,
he had a sort of--
머리가 좀 이상해졌죠
Well, he went a little funny
in the head.
약간 맛이 갔어요
You know, just a little funny.
그러더니 황당한 짓을
저질렀습니다
And he went and did a silly thing.
말씀 드릴게요
I'll tell you what he did.
소련을 침공하라고...
He ordered his planes...
폭격기에
명령을 내렸습니다
...to attack your country.
얘기 안 끝났어요
Let me finish, Dimitri.
끝까지 들으시죠
그럼, 내 기분은 어떻겠소?
Listen, how do you think
I feel about it?
내 기분은 어떤지
상상이 갑니까?
Can you imagine how I feel
about it, Dimitri?
내가 전화는 왜 했겠소?
Why do you think I'm calling you?
안부나 전하려고?
Just to say hello?
당연히 통화하고 싶죠!
Of course I like to speak to you!
물론 안부도 전하고요!
Of course I like to say hello!
지금 말고 다음에 합시다
Not now, but anytime, Dimitri.
끔찍한 일이 생겼다는
얘길 하고 싶었소
I'm just calling up to tell you
something terrible has happened.
물론, 우호적인 전화요
Of course, it's a friendly call.
우호적이지 않다면
전화는 왜 했겠소?
Listen, if it wasn't friendly,
you probably wouldn't have even got it.
폭격까진 1시간도
더 남았소
They will not reach their targets
for at least another hour.
확실합니다
I am positive, Dimitri.
대사와는
이미 얘기가 끝났죠
I've been all over this
with your ambassador.
속임수가 아닙니다
It is not a trick.
잘 들으십시오
I'll tell you.
폭격기의 목표물에 대한
상세한 계획과
We'd like to give your Air Staff
a complete rundown on the targets...
방어시스템
정보를 주겠소
...the flight plans
and defensive systems of the planes.
Yes, if we're unable
to recall the planes...
만약 폭격기들을
저지하지 못한다면
그때는...
...I'd say, well...
그들을 쳐부수도록
도와드리죠
...we're just gonna have to help you
destroy them, Dimitri.
아군인 건
저도 압니다
I know they're our boys.
그럼 누구한테
연락합니까?
Listen. Now, who should we call?
누구요?
잘 안 들리는데요
Who should we call?
Sorry, you faded away.
중앙 인민 공군 기지요?
The Peoples Central
Air Defense Headquarters.
그게 어디 있죠?
Where is that, Dimitri?
옴스크에 있군요
In Omsk. Right.
네
Yes.
먼저 전화를 넣어주겠소?
You'll call them first, will you?
혹시 거기
전화 번호를 압니까?
Do you happen to have the phone number
on you, Dimitri?
옴스크 안내소에
문의하라고요?
What? I see.
Just ask for Omsk information.
나도 유감입니다
어떻게 이런 일이...
I'm sorry too, Dimitri.
I'm very sorry.
당신이 더 유감이겠지만
나도 만만치 않습니다
All right, you're sorrier than I am.
But I am sorry as well.
당신만큼은 유감이오
I am as sorry as you are, Dimitri.
나보다 유감이란 말은
그만 하시오
Don't say that you're more sorry
than I am...
당신만큼
나도 심란하니까
...because I'm capable of being
just as sorry as you are.
쌍방이 유감이라고요
So we're both sorry, all right?
좋아요
All right.
옆에 있소
그럼요, 바꿔드리죠
Yes, he's right here. Yes, he wants
to talk to you. Just a second.
뭡니까?
What?
왜 그럽니까?
What? What is it? What?
멍청한 놈들, 미쳤군
The fools. The mad fools.
왜 그러시오?
What's happened?
심판의 무기 때문이오
The doomsday machine.
심판의 무기?
그게 뭡니까?
The doomsday machine?
What is that?
지구상의 인류와 생태계를
파괴할 만한 무기죠
A device which will destroy
all human and animal life on Earth.
인류와 생태계를?
All human and animal life?
- 대령?
- 부르셨어요?
- Mandrake?
- Yes, Jack?
빨갱이들이 물 마시는 거
본 적 있나?
Have you ever seen a Commie
drink a glass of water?
없는 것 같은데요
Well, I can't say I have, Jack.
물은 절대 안 마시고
대신 보드카를 마시지
Vodka. That's what they drink,
isn't it? Never water.
그렇다고 들었습니다
I believe that's what they drink, yes.
빨갱이들은
절대 물을 안 마셔
On no account will a Commie
ever drink water...
특별한 이유도 없지
...and not without good reason.
그렇군요
Oh, yes.
무슨 말씀 하시려는지
모르겠군요
I can't quite see
what you're getting at.
물이라네
물에 대한 얘기야
Water. That's what I'm getting at.
Water.
모든 생명의 근원은
물이야
Mandrake, water is the source
of all life.
지표의 10분의 7이
물이라네
Seven-tenths of this Earth's surface
is water.
자네의 70%는...
Why, do you realize that...
물로 이뤄진 거 아나?
...70% of you is water?
세상에
Good Lord.
인간의 체액을
공급하기 위해선
And as human beings,
you and I need fresh, pure water...
무공해의 물이 필요해
...to replenish
our precious bodily fluids.
- 알아듣겠나?
- 네
- You beginning to understand?
- Yes.
내가 왜 증류수나
빗물이 아니면
Have you never wondered why I drink
only distilled water...
에틸 알코올만 마시는지
궁금하지 않나?
...or rainwater,
and only pure grain alcohol?
궁금했습니다
It did occur to me, Jack, yes.
물에 불소 처리하는 거
들어봤나?
Have you ever heard of fluoridation
of water?
들어봤습니다
Yes, I have heard of that, Jack, yes.
그게 뭔지 알아?
Do you know what it is?
아뇨, 모릅니다
No, no, I don't know what it is.
그것이야말로
사상최대의
Do you realize that fluoridation...
극악무도하고 위험한
...is the most monstrously conceived...
공산주의자들의
음모라는 걸 아나?
...and dangerous Communist plot
we have ever had to face?